[SPEAKER_00]: You could say something about the... what the characteristics of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, in the... if somebody sees the dhamma, sees that, ah, this dhamma is svaṭkāttho, saṅdhītthiko, akhāṃkabhu, so what's... what... what do they... what do they refer to?
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: First of all, I mean, you said something about svakkhato bhagavata dhammo, so it's well expounded, or it's well described, well told.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I've heard it means things like it's, it is to be experienced, no, it can be understood in this very life, or it's timeless principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it can literally mean anything for people, as... and that's the case with any suttas as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can take them to be like a poetic inspiration, or you can assume that they mean something much more accurately.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you have to approach with the assumption, what they are for, and what their purpose is, and what they mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, if you are self-transparent, and you have some decent habit of self-reflection, you would question.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your assumption in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say you assume suttas to mean, you know, kind of loose folklore, poetic inspiration of, you know, talking about a life that's worth living as a renunciate and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's correct, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can take them to mean that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if you start to read the same suttas, you get to find out that if you were to understand what the Buddha is teaching, you will be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be fully enlightened, on the other hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you revise your assumption what suttas are and what they mean and see whether your current understanding, and nobody denies there is some understanding of it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that making you an arahant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is that making you a sotāpāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, like, right here, right now, do I have results of this understanding?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, well, I'm not yet, but I know I will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you know that if you're not yet?
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, if you see that you don't have something to show for, so to speak, you're not free from suffering, you've done away out of the escape out of the arisen suffering, then you need to re-evaluate your assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, okay, so
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, consequently, what if I were to assume that suttas mean much more accurate things than this romantic poetic inspiration?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eh... you... you approach them in that manner, and then... which means, correspondingly, you have to make that amount of effort to understand it, and then you get to see that you'll be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And nothing has changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even back in the day, you understand the Buddha's discourse, you're a Sotāpanna or an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So today, you understand the Buddha's discourse, you're a Sotāpanna or an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not, it means because you haven't understood
[SPEAKER_01]: So, same goes for the term akālika.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, it can mean timeless and, you know, it's beyond time, it will last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems like lies and really something to strive for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anybody can understand that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that understanding make an arahant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or a sotāpanna, at least?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, suttas say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you understand the dhamma, the characteristics of the dhamma, means you understand the way out of suffering, means you at least have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you think you understood what akālika means, is there a right view arising as a result of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the questioning a person should do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if there is no right view, it means the understanding is not adequate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, without that self-reflection, there is no really base for communication.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just going to be, well, that sutta means this for me, and it might mean something else for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're honest to yourself, you realize, well, not... both of us cannot be right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there are two different meanings.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, different people can have a different understanding of what akālaka means.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mm.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what's important is the understanding of the Buddha's... Well, exactly, because... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha was not just throwing these understandings for the sake of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was teaching them because they result in freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even when sometimes the Buddha was talking about things that are indirectly related to the dhamma, even that, it was actually related to some purpose he was making, some point he was making, for the sake of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he was talking about a previous life, or future lives, or different places of rebirth, he was in the context of people who were listening, for whom that will cause sense of urgency, so they'll practice in this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wasn't, you know, giving a social commentary.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the on the current Brahmin caste system or something, it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering and freedom from it is the only purpose of his entire teaching, 40 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you say he wasn't really explaining anything?
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Explanation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's describing something you need to see for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I explain it to you, you can take it or leave it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you won't get it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you think now explanation is what I was talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can explain to you Four Noble Truths, and you can make perfect sense out of it, and yet you're still not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But instead, I can describe Four Noble Truths, abstain from explaining it to you, and then you will have to recognize, or rather there is a better chance of recognizing,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, oh, this is something that I need to see for myself in order for it to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: I cannot have a notion that, yes, I know what four noble truths are, and at the same time, I know that I'm not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you know what four noble truths are, you are free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, I mean, I can explain to you, and if you are self-transparent, you will not take that explanation wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will know where to apply it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most people, especially the ones with the other right view, which is vast majority, they don't know that and immediately... explanation immediately means, oh, I made sense out of it, thus I understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's well expounded.
[SPEAKER_01]: That first characteristic means that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will...
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha was the foremost in expounding the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, that's a skill in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it does always require the other party to meet you halfway.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's leading on, it's upanāyaka.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not leading... What's the translation?
[SPEAKER_00]: Leading inwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you're a sort of tree-hugging, flower-loving, Buddhist spiritualist, then it leads you to the dhamma inwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, yeah, leading inwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's poetically pleasing or leads you inwards to your heart or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what understanding arises on account of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you saying that outwards is the problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, root of your suffering are things that are out there in the world?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's not what we said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, leading inwards, leading outwards, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: In and out, in and out, like in or out, both in and out, none of that contains the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your craving in regard to inwards, your craving in regard to outwards, your craving in regard to both.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you choose to translate it as leading inwards, and again, it will be like a beautiful reading verse, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing else for you to do there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You made sense out of it, makes you feel good, and you think, okay, I understood what I meant by this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And at the same time, I know I'm still not a Sotāpanna yet, but I must be at some point in the future, because, look, all these things on account of dhamma are pleasing me
[SPEAKER_01]: So, akālika means timeless, means not pertaining to time, not involving time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to sit here, talk to me, eh... without your body being there alive, at the same time?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Was your body alive before?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now your mind is here communicating with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was my body alive before?
[SPEAKER_01]: Eh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, is your mind to now, result of your body being alive before?
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you say, yes, it is, is there a more accurate way of describing that relationship?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it seems to me, yes, that any notions of what my body was doing before are secondary to the fact that there's a body here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even the the commonly misunderstood causation between this is first and this is the result of it,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually already contained within the causation of that simultaneous presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Timeless presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: A presence that doesn't require time to pass.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can say, yes, I'm talking to you because if I weren't alive yesterday or this morning, I wouldn't be able to talk here today to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's absolutely right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not accurate enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even more accurately, you can say, if I'm not alive right here, right now, if this heart is not beating right here, right now,
[SPEAKER_01]: Lungs breathing right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I could not talk to you right here, right now, which is what I'm doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if...
[SPEAKER_01]: I couldn't imagine the past, I can't imagine the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you remember you were alive yesterday?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Except on the basis of being alive today.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's that wrong order that you put your memory first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, because it's this, basically, a view of linear kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you put that first.
[SPEAKER_00]: You put the travel first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can take the notion of yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remember when you were a kid, when you were slightly older, when you were an adult, you remember now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yes, you can choose to focus on these individual aspects that have changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But how would you even know to relate them, unless there is a certain unity that still persists?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you then connect memory of you in the past with memory today?
[SPEAKER_01]: It would simply be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless there is a unifying basis of your center-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you say that you...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about discerning the necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something which is more encompassing than just traveling through time, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but give me a practical example.
[SPEAKER_00]: My body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you reckon, like, kind of... putting that...
[SPEAKER_00]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you have the idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: So somebody hears this now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so I'll practice mindfulness of the body to develop this simultaneous principle that these monks keep talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, that idea already is secondary to the body being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already within the simultaneous principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even before you make the effort to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you think, I'll practice mindfulness of the body, without that base of the body being there provided for you, as a possibility?
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, with that body there, already enduring, there is your practice of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or practice of non-mindfulness, depending which way you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even linear pursuits, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, this is the cause, this is the result, trying to figure it out, is secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's dependent upon the simultaneously enduring life, or body, or any other aspect, feeling, any other aggregate you want to take.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what Buddha meant when he described the five aggregates, when he came to the aggregates of saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, what is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he describes five aggregates again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whichever way you look, it's the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: They depend on the five aggregates, which is why you can look at them, and attend to them, and act out of them, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all within that dependence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that dependence does not involve time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the notion of duration, which is what the notion of time is, it's already within that dependence on those same aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you would have no notion of duration, because there's no reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what, like, simultaneous principle, when we talked about it, it does not mean, oh, you look at the two things that are simultaneously, oh, look, this and this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You left yourself out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneous principle means, with this as a basis, this is the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with this, this is, or with this, there is the being of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whichever way you want to translate it, both are in the present tense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, you can also say, well, it's not in that immediate present tense.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in the present tense of this life, or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, but then ask yourself, in the beginning, like what I said, you should ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that understanding result in direct inability to suffer amid suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because anybody can take it or leave it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, Patitsaṃpada applies to this life, or three lives, or six lives, or twenty-seven lives.
[SPEAKER_01]: But does that understanding free you from suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how about you then try to understand it in a way that will free you from suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the Buddha said it himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The one who understands Patitsaṃpada understands the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: One who understands the dhamma understands Patitsaṃpada
[SPEAKER_01]: ...sees it for himself, directly, as a result of which he cannot suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why there are no alternative interpretations of patisambhāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the principle of the dhamma that, if understood, results in you being unable to suffer amidst suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's another simultaneous principle, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: With suffering, non-suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, oh, with suffering, later I don't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's management.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's psychotherapy.
[SPEAKER_01]: With suffering present, I don't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if you haven't understood the simultaneous principle, with suffering present, I suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like anything is situated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within a... Not anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I say anything, I mean anything I can experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is already based on your situated experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are always in a situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means there is always a presently enduring feeling, presently enduring intentions, presently enduring perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you say that?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.